Chapter 77.
the great H highidleberg ton.
Now comes the bailing of the case. But to comprehend it a right, you must know
something of the curious internal structure of the thing operated upon.
Regarding the sperm whale's head as a solid oblong, you may on an inclined
plane sideways divide it into two coins whereof the lower is the bony structure
forming the cranium and jaws and the upper anxious mass wholly free from
bones. Its broad forward end forming the expanded vertical apparent forehead of
the whale. at the middle of the forehead. Horizontally subdivide this
upper coin and then you have two almost equal parts which before were naturally
divided by an internal wall of a thick tenderous substance.
Footnote coin is not a uklitian term. It belongs to the pure nautical
mathematics. I know not that it has been defined before. A coin is a solid which
differs from a wedge in having its sharp end formed by the steep inclination of
one side instead of the mutual tapering of both sides.
End of footnote.
The lower subdivided part called the junk is one immense honeycomb of oil
formed by the crossing and recrossing into 10,000 infiltrated cells of tough
elastic white fibers throughout its whole extent. The upper part known as
the case may be regarded as the great h highidleberg ton of the sperm whale. And
as that famous great tears is mystically carved in front, so the whale's vast
pleated forehead forms innumerable strange devices for the emblematical
adornment of his wondrous tongue.
Moreover, as that of H Highidleberg was always replenished with the most
excellent of wines from the Renish valleys, so the ton of the whale
contains by far the most precious of all his oily vintages, namely the highly
prized spermaceti in its absolutely pure, limpid, and odoriferous state. Nor
is this precious substance found unaloyed in any other part of the
creature. Though in life it remains perfectly fluid, yet upon exposure to
the air after death, it soon begins to concrete, sending forth beautiful
crystallin shoots, as when the first thin delicate ice is just forming in water.
A large whale's case generally yields about 500 gall of sperm, though from
unavoidable circumstances considerable of it is spilled, leaks, and dribbles
away, or is otherwise irrevocably lost in the ticklish business of securing what you can.
I know not with what fine and costly material the H Highleberg ton was coated
within, but in superlative richness that coating could not possibly have compared
with the silken pearl colored membrane like the lining of a fine police forming
the inner surface of the sperm whale's case.
It will have been seen that the h highidleberg ton of the sperm whale
embraces the entire length of the entire top of the head. And since, as has been
elsewhere set forth, the head embraces 1/3 of the whole length of the creature,
then setting that length down at 80 ft for a goodsiz whale, you have more than
26 ft for the depth of the ton when it is lengthwise hoisted up and down
against the ship's side. As in decapitating the whale, the operator's
instrument is brought close to the spot where an entrance is subsequently forced
into the spermaceti magazine. He has, therefore, to be uncommonly heedful,
lest a careless, untimely stroke should invade the sanctuary and wastingly let
out its invaluable contents. It is this decapitated end of the head also which
is at last elevated out of the water and retained in that position by the
enormous cutting tackles whose hemp and combinations on one side make quite a
wilderness of ropes in that quarter.
Thus much being said, attend now, I pray you, to that marvelous, and in this
particular instance almost fatal operation whereby the sperm whale's
great H Highleberg ton is tapped.